NICHOLAS SPYRISON

DATA SCIENTIST

Professional Summary

I am a published data scientist with extensive experience with a wide variety of multivariate data. I am client-focused, results-orientated with a passion for using data visualization, complex analysis, and factor analysis to simplify complicated problems into interpretable takeaways.

SKILLS

Strengths	Data vis, dimension reduction, feature engineering, machine learning & interpretability
Programs	R, Python, Git & GitHub, Excel & VBA, LATEX
Packages	ggplot2, tidyverse, plotly, shiny, tidymodels, caret, DALEX, keras, pandas, scikit-learn
Models	xgboost, neural networks, random forest, SVM, logistic, K-NN, K-means, parameter tuning
Databases	T-SQL, OR ACLE, OLAP/MOLAP, MongoDB
REPORTING	Rmarkdown, Shiny, SSRS, Tableau, PowerBI, WebFOCUS, Crystal

SOFTWARE (R PACKAGES)

SPINIFEX	Facilitates the manual tour. Provides an interface for composing animated and interactive	
	linear projections to various formats.	<u>nk</u>
CHEEM	Given a nonlinear model, find the local explanation of each observation. Provides an interacti	ive
	coordinated views in a shiny application. Novel analysis and visuals to explore the loc	cal
	explanations with the manual tour. This general analysis is demonstrated on SHAP value	ies
	from random forest models.	nk

EDUCATION

Degree	Ph.D., Information Technology/Stats	under examination, 2018 — Now
University	Monash University	Melbourne, Australia
Focus	Dimension reduction, interactive and dynamic data visualization, machine learning models and interpretability	
Thesis	Interactive and dynamic visualization of high-dimension	nal data <u>Link</u>
Degree University	B.Sc, Statistics, Physics & Mathematics minors Iowa State University	2008 — 2012 Ames, Iowa

WORK EXPERIENCE

Job Title	Various seasonal employment	part time during education, 2018 — Now
Employer	Monash University	Melbourne, Australia
Programs	R, Git, PowerBI, API	

Data fluency instructor: taught various workshops on R, modeling, programming, PowerBI, and Git & GitHub, *Teaching assistant*: data exploration and visualization & business and economic statistics, *Research officer*: criminology & human geology data cleaning, analysis, summarization & reporting.

JOB TITLEBusiness Intelligence Developer2016 — 2018EMPLOYERCPI Card GroupDenver, CO

PROGRAMS T-SQL, SSRS, Crystal, Oracle BICS, Excel

Develop mid- and high-abstraction database queries. Database reporting; across 4 reporting platforms. Developed supply chain report enabling a cost reduction of more than \$4M USD within one plant.

JOB TITLEBusiness Intelligence Developer2015 — 2016EMPLOYERUDR Real Estate Investment TrustDenver, CO

Programs T-SQL, SSRS, OLAP/MOLAP, WebFOCUS

Query, analysis, & reporting. Organized and conducted transition from WebFOCUS reporting to SSRS. On-call for enterprise-wide ETL process.

JOB TITLE Business Intelligence Analyst 2014 — 2015
EMPLOYER Heartland Financial USA Dubuque, IA
PROGRAMS T-SQL, WebFOCUS

Database querying, data analysis and enterprise reporting.

JOB TITLE Delivery Data Analyst

EMPLOYER IBM — International Business Machines

PROGRAMS R, Excel, VBA

2013 — 2014

Dubuque, IA

Statistical variance analysis & metric reporting to teams and management. IBM's lean/six sigma methodology, root cause analysis, ETL scripting via VBA macros for 0.5 FTE savings across the team. Step-wise model selection with dozens of variables, predicting ticket time.

JOB TITLE Various seasonal employment part time during education, 2010 — 2012
EMPLOYER Iowa State University & Ames Laboratory
Ames, IA

User Interface Developer: Custom R application *Laboratory Technician*: Superconductivity data measurement and analysis, *Physics Tutor*: Classical Physics (201) to groups of 5 students.

Honors and awards

Monash Postgraduate publication Award 2022 Melbourne Datathon 2020, Insights category — 1st place $\underline{\mathtt{Link}} - \mathtt{2020}$ ACEMS Impact and Engagement Award 2018 UseR2018 Datathon — 3rd place 2018 Faculty Graduate Research Scholarship 2018 - 2022 Co-funded Monash Graduate Scholarship 2018 - 2022 Nominated for Student Employee of the Year 2011 & 2012 American Legion award 2008

Membership & engagement

Australian Centre of Excellence for Mathematical and Statistical Frontiers (ACEMS) Statistical Society of Australia (SSA), Victorian branch American Statistical Association, district 4

REFERENCES

Professor Di Cook, PhD supervisor Professor Kim Marriott, PhD supervisor Email: dicook@monash.edu, Office: +61 (0)3 9905 2608 Email: kim.marriott@monash.edu, Office: +61 (0)3 9905 5525

Doctoral thesis

[1] Nicholas S Spyrison. "Interactive and dynamic visualization of high-dimensional data". en. PhD thesis. Monash University, Mar. 2022. URL: https://github.com/nspyrison/thesis_ns/blob/master/docs/thesis_ns.pdf.

JOURNAL ARTICLES

- [2] Nicholas Spyrison and Dianne Cook. "spinifex: an R Package for Creating a Manual Tour of Low-dimensional Projections of Multivariate Data". en. In: *The R Journal* 12.1 (2020), p. 243. ISSN: 2073-4859. DOI: 10.32614/RJ-2020-027. URL: https://journal.r-project.org/archive/2020/RJ-2020-027/index.html (visited on 10/16/2020).
- [3] Stuart Lee et al. "The state-of-the-art on tours for dynamic visualization of high-dimensional data". en. In: WIREs Computational Statistics (Dec. 2021), p. 21. ISSN: 1939-0068. DOI: 10.1002/wics.1573. URL: https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1002/wics.1573 (visited on 12/10/2021).

SOFTWARE (R PACKAGES)

- [4] Nicholas Spyrison and Dianne Cook. spinifex: Manual Tours, Manual Control of Dynamic Projections of Numeric Multivariate Data. 2021. URL: https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=spinifex.
- [5] Nicholas Spyrison. cheem: Interactively Explore the Support of Local Explanations of a Model. 2022. URL: https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=cheem.

Conference proceedings

- [6] Nicholas S. Spyrison. "spinifex: visualizing local structure of higher dimensions". en. In: Brisbane, Australia, 2018. URL: https://user2018.r-project.org/poster/(visited on 07/28/2020).
- [7] Madeleine Barrow, Jieyang Chong, and Nicholas Spyrison. "Changes to Victorian Intraday Electricity Demand Following COVID-19 Restrictions". en. In: *Melbourne Datathon 2020, Insights category*. Oct. 2020, p. 4. URL: https://github.com/nspyrison/melb_datathon2020/blob/master/_paper/paper.pdf (visited on 02/09/2022).
- [8] Nicholas Spyrison, Benjamin Lee, and Lonni Besançon. ""Is IEEE VIS *that* good?" On key factors in the initial assessment of manuscript and venue quality". In: *IEEE AltVis Workshop*. type: article. July 2021. DOI: 10.31219/osf.io/65wm7. URL: https://osf.io/65wm7/ (visited on 08/21/2021).